Jonathan Demers

Montreal, QC, H4J 1K5, Canada jdemers@opcodesolutions.com linkedin.com/in/jonathan-demers-ing Latest version: MD, HTML, PDF

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING LEADER

Highly technical and result driven leader with 18 years experience in Technology, including 12 years as consultant for diverse enterprises. Fast learner and strategic decision maker, with natural ability to perform in fast paced environments. Played critical roles on high-visibility projects in various organizational structures and company sizes. Thorough understanding of both organizational and technical stakes of software development life cycle (SDLC) and the relationship between them.

Leadership	Technical
✓ Organizational Leadership ✓ Strategic Planning	✓ Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC)
✓ Team Coordination ✓ Talent Management ✓ Coaching	✓ Agile Methodologies ✓ Architecture ✓ Distributed Systems
✓ Vision Alignment ✓ Goal Setting ✓ Team Leadership	✓ Design Patterns ✓ REST ✓ SOA ✓ Web Services
✓ Communication ✓ Management	✓ System Integration ✓ Development

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

TD Bank - Development Lead (Consultant)

Jun 2018 - Present

- Lead teams of developers and devops on numerous successful enterprise projects.
- Advise the department leader on organizational matters.
- Contribute to new A/B infrastructure and architecture vision and designs.
- Advise on project and delivery planning.
- Facilitate communication between business stakeholders and technical teams.

Projects: GPS 2.1, GPS 2.2 and much more. Multiple system integrations. Buy online. Customer facing applications: Mylnsurance, DigitalQuoter.

Technologies: Java, Spring, Maven, JBoss, OAuth 2.0, REST, Soap, Angular, Typescript, NodeJS, PM2, npm, Oracle, Linux (RHEL), Git, Atlassian suite (Bitbucket, Jira, confluence, etc.), CDN, Private Cloud, CI/CD, Jenkins, Ansible, Docker, Agile methodology.

OpCode Solutions - Leader & Consultant - Software Engineering

Aug 2008 - Present

This is the company through which I provide technology consulting services, including organizational leadership, infrastructure & architecture vision, strategy and execution.

Pstox - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)

Contribute to architecture and development of ThinkingCapital's online financing platform for businesses, which got successfully acquired by Purpose Financial. Multiple system integrations, including SalesForce and Equifax.

Technologies: Mule ESB EE, Java 8, JPA, MariaDB (MySQL), REST, JSON, OAuth2, JWT, Auth0, Swagger, Spring Boot, Elasticsearch, Docker, Maven, Anypoint Studio, Eclipse, Git, Jenkins, Jira, JMeter, etc.

Morgan Stanley - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)

Sep 2015 - Apr 2017

Contribute to architecture and development of real-time pricing of fixed income securities and search platform used by financial advisors. Lead 2 developers.

Technologies: Java 8, Scala, Linux, DB2, WebSphere MQ, Spring, Hibernate, Spring, Play, SBT, Git, Autosys, Kerberos, Linux, etc.

Intact - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)

Jul 2013 - Jan 2014

Contribute to development of new insurance policy management system on service oriented architecture (SOA backend). Project: PAS.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, Websphere, SOAP, JAXB, XSD, WSDL, Spring, Hibernate, Oracle, RAD, RTC (Jazz: Source and work item).

Industrial Alliance Securities - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)

Feb 2013 - Jul 2013

- Contribute to architecture and development of new fixed income trading platform (Bond Trader).
- Integration with Bloomberg TOMS for real-time price feed and trade capture report over FIX protocol and real time trade feed over Bloomberg proprietary protocol.
- Integration with CBID's external trading platform to submit orders and receive executions over FIX protocol.
- Integration with IBM ISM (SIS) to send phase1 files automatically in real time (DP trades) and at the end of day (normal trades) via SFTP.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, Tomcat, Mule ESB, QuickFIX/J, JSch, Spring, JSON, HTML, CSS, JQuery, Linux (Ubuntu Server), MySQL.

Desjardins - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)

Aug 2012 - Feb 2013

Lead backend development of new online trading platform (Stocks, Options, Mutual Funds, etc). Provide technical leadership and architecture vision.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, Tomcat, Weblogic, Mule ESB, Spring, JSON, Linux (Red Hat), SunOS, MySQL.

Gemalto (now Thales) - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)

Oct 2011 - Jul 2012

Develop mobile banking solution framework on backend and frontend (Android).

Technologies: Java/J2EE, OSGi, Jetty, Hibernate, Android SDK, SOAP, Linux (Red Hat), Oracle.

Desjardins - Senior Software Developer (Consultant)

Contribute to architecture and development of new Stocks/Options trading system. Integration with IBM OSS servers over MQ. Migrate other existing Java applications to HA infrastructure.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, Tomcat, Mule ESB, Spring, Websphere MQv7, ActiveMQ, Linux (Red Hat), MySQL.

Penson Financial Services - Senior Software Developer (Consultant)

Apr 2010 - Oct 2010

Migrate and enhance several financial applications from IBM ISM platform to Broadridge platform.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, Tomcat, Struts, Hibernate, Linux (Debian), MS SQL server.

Gemalto (now Thales) - Senior Software Developer (Consultant)

Aug 2008 - Oct 2009

Contribute to development of mobile instant messaging and mobile banking applications (backend). In charge of performance/stability assessment and optimizations.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, OSGi, Jetty, SOAP, Linux (Red Hat), Oracle, JMeter.

Tecsys - Solutions Architect / Software Developer

Mar 2006 - Jul 2008

Develop Supply Chain Management applications. Started as software developer in R&D and got promoted to solutions architect in Custom Enhancement department.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, JBoss, Websphere, JAX-WS, AIX, Linux, Oracle, Informix.

Morgan Stanley - Systems Architect

Aug 2004 - Mar 2006

Contribute to development of distributed financial system for trade allocation of fixed income securities. Consultant for Morgan Stanley in Fixed Income Division (Employee of Compuware).

Technologies: Java/J2EE, JXB (proprietary app framework), CPS (proprietary pub-sub engine), Tomcat, SOAP, IBM MQSeries, Linux, Sybase.

Logient - Software Developer

Dec 2002 - Aug 2004

Develop various applications, from generic CMS to custom E-Commerce solutions.

Technologies: Java/J2EE, Tomcat, Resin, Servlet, Jsp, Taglibs, XML, DTD, XSLT, XPaths, Linux, Oracle, PostgreSQL, Html, Javascript.

Institut de recherche d'Hydro-Quebec - Software Developer

May 2002 - Dec 2002

Develop real-time software and hardware integration for underwater robot used for the inspection of hydroelectric dams. R&D, robotics department.

Technologies: C++, MICROB robotic library, Inertial navigation system, Kalman Filter, QNX Real Time OS.

Intern - Canadian Space Agency

Apr 2001 - Aug 2001

Develop testbed to measure the performance of spatial RF communication modules.

Technologies: MatLab, LabView, RF Lab equipment (spectrum analyzers, network analyzers, arbitrary signal generators, etc).

CERTIFICATIONS

deeplearning.ai - Artificial Intelligence - TensorFlow in Practice

• Issued 2020 - 4 courses, 16 weeks. Certificate of completion

deeplearning.ai - Artificial Intelligence - Deep Learning

• Issued 2019 - 5 courses, 16 weeks. Certificate of completion

MuleSoft - MuleSoft Certified Developer - Integration and API Associate

• Issued 2017 (2 years validity). Certificate of completion

EDUCATION

University of Michigan - Specialization, Organizational Leadership

2017 - 2018 Credential ID HRYMS5AB3PTJ

This 5-Star "Leading People and Teams Specialization" from Michigan faculty strengthen essential leadership skills with proven management techniques. It also includes interviews with exceptional leaders Jeff Brodsky, Global Head of HR for Morgan Stanley, and John Beilein, Head Coach of the University of Michigan Men's Basketball Team. The specialization has 5 courses over 20 weeks.

Grade Achieved: 99%

Polytechnique Montréal - B.Eng., Engineering - Telecommunications

1998 - 2002

- Mention of excellence from the general director for academic achievement.
- Scholarship for academic excellence.
- Achieved unconditional admission to PhD directly (skipping Master), I did not pursue this goal.

GPA: 3.8 (max of 4.0 at Polytechnique)